Welcome!
ようこそ 今月のプログラムを視聴
してくださって ありがとうございます
We’re so happy you can join us
for this month’s program.
I’m here with my good friend
今日は 親友の
レオン･ウィーバー兄弟と一緒です
and cohost, Leon Weaver.
There he is.
ウィーバー兄弟 ようこそ
Leon, welcome!
お招き ありがとうございます
David, I’m delighted to be here with you.
ウィーバー兄弟について
少しお話ししたいと思います
Now, I’d like to tell you
a little something about Leon.
When I was invited into Bethel in 1990,
私は1990年にベテルに来た時
I was assigned to the Service Department
奉仕部門に割り当てられました
そこの監督の1人が
ウィーバー兄弟だったんです
and Leon was one of the overseers.
Now, in the Service Department,
奉仕部門ではとても難しい
問題を扱うことがあるので
at times we had to deal
with some very difficult matters
アドバイスが欲しいことがありました
and sometimes you needed advice.
And I could always rely
on Leon to help me out.
そんなときはよく
ウィーバー兄弟に相談しました
兄弟の事務所に行くと
どんなに忙しい時でも手を止めて
I’d go into his office,
he’d set aside whatever it was
he was working on,
私の話をじっくり聞き
アドバイスをくれました
he’d listen, and then he’d give his input.
I really appreciated the experience
I acquired in the Service Department,
奉仕部門でいろいろ
学べたことに感謝しています
ウィーバー兄弟からも
たくさん学ぶことができました
and Leon was certainly part of it.
So this is one reason why I have love
そういう訳で 兄弟のことが
大好きですし 尊敬しています
and respect for that brother.
Now, Leon, what can we look forward to
in this month’s program?
ウィーバー兄弟 今月は
どんなプログラムでしょうか
Many years ago,
何十年も前 バルネーブ姉妹は
Elizabeth gave up a prestigious career
エホバにもっと仕えるために
華やかな仕事を辞めました
to do more for Jehovah.
How did her decision
その結果 姉妹の人生は
どう変わりましたか
change the course of her life?
And we’ll debut a fascinating new series.
新しいシリーズも始まります
エホバの証人の歴史のさまざまな面に
スポットが当てられます
It will reveal aspects
of our theocratic history
you may not be familiar with.
きっと新たな発見があるでしょう
That sounds very interesting.
それは楽しみですね
お見逃しなく
Don’t go away!
2021年11月の
JW Broadcasting®です
This is JW Broadcasting® for November 2021.
預言者イザヤを通して
Through his prophet Isaiah,
Jehovah made a wonderful promise,
エホバは素晴らしい約束をしました
one that’s being fulfilled today.
それは今実現しています
We can read about it at Isaiah 60:17:
読んでみましょう
イザヤ 60:17です
“Instead of the copper I will bring in gold,
「私は銅を金に替え
“and instead of the iron
I will bring in silver,
鉄を銀に 木を銅に
“instead of the wood, copper,
“and instead of the stones, iron;
石を鉄に替える
“and I will appoint peace as your overseers
平和をあなたの監督とし
and righteousness as your task assigners.”
正義をあなたの管理者とする」
Well, now, this reference to “overseers”
ここにある「監督」とか
and “task assigners”
—that sounds like organization, doesn’t it?
「管理者」という言葉は
組織をイメージさせます
So, what is Jehovah telling us?
エホバはどんなことを言っていますか
He’s saying that we can expect
私たちは組織の取り決めが
to see organizational arrangements
getting better and better.
徐々に良くなっていくのを
見ることができる ということです
Well, if you’ve been associated
with the truth for a while,
長年エホバに仕えてきた方なら
イザヤのこの預言が実現してきたことに
同意なさると思います
I’m sure you’ll agree that Isaiah’s prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
So for this broadcast,
この話では 第2次世界大戦後の
進展について振り返りたいと思います
I thought we’d review
some of the improvements
we’ve seen just since World War II.
That’s the period
most of us are familiar with.
多くの人が過ごしてきた時代です
これから取り上げることを
初めて聞く方もいるでしょう
Now, some of you will be hearing
about these things for the first time.
Others will have lived through it all,
実際に経験してきた方もいると思います
and for them it’ll bring back fond memories.
そういう方にとっては
懐かしい思い出でしょう
So let’s go back.
It’ll be fun!
では タイムスリップを楽しみましょう
話の主題は
「あの頃を覚えていますか」です
I call this part
“Do You Remember When . . . ?”
第2次世界大戦前
またその後何年もの間
Before World War II
and for a number of years after that,
many congregations
didn’t have a Kingdom Hall of their own.
多くの会衆は王国会館を
持っていませんでした
They were actually encouraged
実際その頃は 個人の家や
to meet in private homes
借りた施設で集まるよう
勧められていました
or in rented facilities.
借りた施設や個人の家を使う方が
The thinking was that if you
were in a rented facility or a private home,
融通が利く という理由でした
you had more flexibility.
必要に応じて 集会を開く場所を
簡単に変えることができました
You could move the meeting place
from one place to the other very easily.
But there were problems; there were drawbacks.
でも不便な点もありました
Sometimes the space
別の団体が同じ場所を
使うこともあったので
would be shared with other organizations.
集会が終わった後
So you couldn’t leave your
文書 雑誌 演台 音響装置を
置いたままにすることはできません
literature, magazines,
speaker’s stand, and maybe even a sound system
in the hall at the end of the meeting.
When the meeting was over,
you’d have to pack it all up
そういう物を全部まとめて
持って帰らなければなりませんでした
and take it away.
それだけではありません
But that’s not all.
Sometimes you had to arrive very early
and clean the place up
会場にかなり早く着いて
掃除しなければならない
こともありました
after a particularly rowdy group
of people had used it.
マナーが悪い人たちが
使った後は特にそうです
And if there were cigar smokers
in that group, you were in trouble.
その中にたばこを吸う人たちが
いたら 大変でした
集会前に空気を入れ換えようとしても
It was very difficult to air the place out
in time for the meeting.
そう簡単にはいきません
Now, remember, in those days,
people could smoke in a private hall,
当時は 民間の会場でたばこを
吸うことが許されていました
and you could smoke in an airplane
—they could smoke almost anywhere.
飛行機でも
ほとんどどこでもそうでした
ですから 私たちは大変でした
So this was a real problem for us.
ほかにも問題がありました
There were other problems.
私たちの生まれ故郷で
王国会館ができる前のことです
Before we had a Kingdom Hall in my hometown,
the congregation met in a rented facility.
会衆が借りていた会場は
Now, in October,
the place was decorated for Halloween,
10月にはハロウィーンの
飾り付けが行われ
and in December, there was
a great big Christmas tree on the platform.
12月にはステージに大きな
クリスマスツリーが置かれました
撤去できませんでした
We couldn’t move it!
Now, this was in Canada,
当時カナダでは そうした会場に
and portraits
of the King and Queen of England
英国の王と女王の絵が飾られ
as well as the British flag
were permanent fixtures in the hall.
国旗が掲げられていました
You couldn’t remove
any of it for the meeting.
どれも撤去できませんでした
Yet, to their credit,
それでも 聖書に関心を持つ
多くの人たちが集会に出席しました
many interested persons
attended our meetings.
And to them, it wasn’t
the meeting place that was important;
出席者は会場の様子よりも
そこで話される事柄に
注意を向けていたのです
it was what
they were learning there that counted.
Speaking of our meeting places,
当初会衆は
at first, congregations were on their own
自分たちだけで王国会館を
建てなければなりませんでした
when it came to building them.
Now, at times, the most a congregation
中には 土地を買うだけの
お金しかない会衆もありました
could afford was to purchase the land,
and sometimes that land would sit there
その後 建物を建てる
お金を集めるために
for years because it would
take years to get the money together
何年もかかる場合もありました
to build the hall.
And then once they had the money together,
たとえお金が集まったとしても
建設のための技術を持つ兄弟たちの
数は限られていました
were there enough brothers who could take
the lead in the construction?
Sometimes on a weekend, you’d see
1人か2人の兄弟が
時々週末を使って 一生懸命働きました
just one or two brothers working away
at the site of the new hall.
兄弟たちの頑張りには
頭が下がる思いです
You had to love them for their perseverance.
Nowadays,
今は 支部設計建設部門の監督の下
our Kingdom Hall construction
is supervised by the LDCs,
大勢のボランティアが短期間で
with lots of qualified volunteers,
and practical Kingdom Halls
can be constructed in a short period of time.
使いやすい王国会館を建設しています
集会はどうでしたか
What about the meetings?
長年 神権宣教学校も奉仕会も
For years, the Theocratic Ministry School,
Service Meeting,
会衆の書籍研究も
「ものみの塔」研究も約1時間でした
Congregation Book Study,
and Watchtower{
were all about an hour in length.
So were the public talks
時々行われていた公開講演もです
—when we had them.
Now, at first, a public talk
wasn’t scheduled every week.
公開講演は毎週あった
わけではありません
There’d be a series of four or eight talks,
もし講演者がいれば 4つとか8つの
一連の話が行われました
if you could schedule that many speakers.
その後しばらく 公開講演は
行われなくなりました
And then, for a while,
the congregation wouldn’t have a public talk.
Why was that?
なぜでしょうか
Remember,
神権宣教学校が始まったのは
1943年です
the Theocratic Ministry School
didn’t get under way until 1943,
兄弟たちが1時間の話を
行えるようになるまでには
and it took time for the brothers to develop
the skills to deliver an hour talk.
時間がかかりました
But in time, they were delivering
でもやがて 素晴らしい公開講演を
行えるようになりました
excellent public talks!
And do you remember
公開講演のたびに ビラが準備され
when we had individual handbills
講演者の名前も印刷されて
いたことを覚えていますか
for each public talk
with the name of the speaker printed on them?
1959年まで
Until 1959,
only brothers were enrolled in the school.
入校できるのは兄弟だけでした
For some years, during the first few minutes
当時はまず 生徒の
出席確認が行われていました
of the school there was a roll call,
and the names of all the brothers
enrolled in the school were read out.
入校している兄弟全員の
名前が読み上げられました
Now, when your name was read out,
you were to answer, “Present.”
名前が呼ばれたら 「はい」と
言うことになっていました
「来てまーす」なんて
言う人もいましたが
A few rebels would say, “Here.”
But you were supposed to say, “Present.”
「はい」と答えるべきでした
Now, initially,
according to the instructions,
その頃の指示によると
しばらくの期間
きちんとした理由もなく
if anyone was deliberately
and habitually absent over a period of time,
習慣的に休むなら 退学させられる
ことになっていました
he was dropped from the school.
その後 この指示は変更されました
Later, that was discontinued.
Now, the roll-call arrangement
got me into a bit of trouble.
出席確認というと ちょっとした
事件を思い出します
You see, in our congregation
when the roll was being called each week,
私たちの会衆で毎週
生徒たちの名前が呼ばれる時
I noticed that there
were a few young brothers
私より少しだけ年上の兄弟たちが
「はい」と答えていました
who were just a little bit older than I was
who would answer, “Present.”
So one night after the school,
I asked the school servant
それである日 学校の僕に
「次回から私の名前も
呼んでください」とお願いしました
if I could have my name read out
at the next meeting.
He warmly commended me.
兄弟は私を心から褒めてくれました
And sure enough,
I got my name read out the following week.
翌週 私の名前が呼ばれると
Everyone congratulated me after the meeting.
集会後 みんなが褒めてくれました
I couldn’t understand why.
「なんでだろう
『はい』って言っただけなのに」
I only said, “Present.”
The problem was that I didn’t know
that when you got your name read out,
私は知らなかったんですが
名前が呼ばれるということは
話もする ということでした
you were agreeing to give a talk.
I thought I was just signing up
to have my name read out.
私はただ 名前を呼んで
ほしかっただけなんです
2カ月後 1953年4月8日に
Well, a couple of months later,
on April 8, 1953,
初めての8分の話をしました
I delivered my first
eight-minute talk on the theme
主題は 「世の終わりを
ふれ告げる」です
“Proclaiming the World’s Doom.”
当時は聖書朗読が
なかったので 話をしました
Now, why an eight-minute talk?
Well, we didn’t have Bible readings yet.
So when you were on the school,
学校に入ると 8分の話を
することになっていました
you were giving an eight-minute talk.
Well, today, we make sure
everyone understands what’s involved
もちろん今は 週日の集会の
生徒になるというのがどういうことか
in being a student in the midweek meeting.
みんな分かっているはずです
In 1950,
1950年には
we received the New World Translation
英語の「クリスチャン･ギリシャ語聖書
新世界訳」が発表され
of the Christian Greek Scriptures{
集会に持ってくるよう勧められました
and we were encouraged
to bring it to the meetings.
So for the Hebrew Scriptures,
you would have the American Standard Version
ヘブライ語聖書の方は
「アメリカ標準訳」か
「ジェームズ王欽定訳」を使いました
or the King James Version
—mo{
エホバの名が出てくる「アメリカ
標準訳」を使う人が多かったです
because it had Jehovah’s name.
So you’d have two Bibles
to bring to the meeting.
それで 集会には ヘブライ語聖書と
There’s the one for the Hebrew Scriptures
「クリスチャン･ギリシャ語聖書
新世界訳」を持っていきました
and then the New World Translation{
2冊だけです
It wasn’t too bad.
その後 「ヘブライ語聖書
新世界訳」が
But later, the New World Translation {
1巻ずつ発表されました
was released in installments.
So you’d get a volume every year or two.
1, 2年に1巻受け取りました
新しいものを受け取るたびに
And as we received each new volume,
集会に持ってくるよう勧められました
we were encouraged
to bring it to the meeting.
Now, in time, those volumes
started to pile up
その数はだんだん増えていき
1960年には
so that by 1960,
ヘブライ語聖書が全部で
5巻になりました
you might have volumes 1 through 5
of the Hebrew Scriptures,
それに加えて ギリシャ語聖書と
also the Greek Scriptures,
and your regular study aids!
他の出版物を持っていきました
And we had thick study aids in those days.
しかも分厚い本です
ですから 大きくて丈夫な
かばんが必要でした
We had big briefcases
and strong backs in those days.
「新世界訳聖書」が1冊になった時には
We were really happy to get
the complete New World Translation
本当にうれしかったです
in just one volume in 1961.
1961年のことです
音楽についてはどうでしょうか
Now, let’s say a word about music.
That’s something that’s near
and dear to my heart.
私は音楽が大好きです
For many years,
it was left up to the local servants
長年 会衆の集会でどの歌を歌うかは
to decide which songs the congregation
would sing at the meetings.
会衆に任されていました
So the chairman of a particular meeting
would select the songs,
集会の司会者が歌を選びました
でもその歌を歌えないこともありました
but his choice wasn’t always final.
Many Kingdom Halls had a piano
多くの王国会館には 伴奏用に
ピアノなどの楽器がありました
or some other instrument
to accompany the singing.
But often the musician couldn’t play
all of the songs in the book,
伴奏者は全ての曲を
演奏できたわけではないので
so we’d have to sing the songs he could play.
その人が演奏できる曲しか
歌えませんでした
同じ曲を何度も歌ったので
覚えてしまうほどでした
We got to know those few songs really well!
But those humble musicians
did their best to accompany our singing.
伴奏者は私たちのために
頑張って演奏してくれました
Now, as a result of all this,
こんな感じだったので
70年近くたった今でも
the words to those songs
we sang nearly 70 years ago
当時歌った歌を思い出すことができます
still come readily to mind.
これは覚えていますか
Do you remember the written review?
筆記の復習です
Maybe you don’t.
筆記の復習では 過去数週間に
Congregations periodically
had a written review of material
that had been covered
神権宣教学校で学んだ
事柄を振り返りました
in the Theocratic Ministry School
over the previous weeks.
Now, we had a half hour to answer
30分で 25ぐらいの質問に答えます
about 25 questions.
But then, when the half hour was up,
30分たつと
それぞれ自分の名前を書いて
we would write our name on the paper,
hand it in to the school servant,
学校の僕に提出します
学校の僕はそれを家で採点しました
and he would take
all the papers home to grade them.
Now, if there were 25 questions,
you’d get 4 points apiece
質問が25あれば
1問につき4点で
for each correct answer—100 points total.
合計100点になります
And then a week later,
he’d return the papers to us at the meeting.
翌週 学校の僕から答案が返されます
Now, in the early years of the arrangement
(I remember well),
私はよく覚えていますが 昔は
he’d announce the highest
and lowest grade to the congregation.
会衆の最高点と最低点が
発表されました
Now, thankfully, he didn’t mention the names
幸い その人たちの名前は
発表されませんでした
of the one who got
the highest and lowest score.
Well, later, that arrangement to announce
やがて 点数を発表する
取り決めはなくなりました
the highest and lowest grade
was discontinued.
Do you remember when circuit assemblies
巡回大会が金曜日の夕方から
began on Friday evening
日曜日の午後まで行われて
いたことを覚えていますか
and continued through Sunday afternoon?
A full program
土曜日は午後から夜まで
プログラムが続きました
was presented Saturday afternoon and evening.
土曜日の夜は特に面白かったです
There was never a dull moment
on Saturday night.
生き生きとした実演があったので
There were lively demonstrations
that kept our interest
最後まで目が離せませんでした
right up to the end of the program.
かなり凝ったステージのセットが
造られることもありました
Sometimes the sets were very elaborate.
For example,
suppose a publisher was demonstrating
例えば 伝道者が家から家の
伝道をする実演がありました
a presentation from door to door.
今なら ドアを実際に
準備することはありません
Now, today
we’d just imagine there was a door.
But back then at the circuit assembly,
でも当時の巡回大会では
ステージ上にドアのセットが
造られることもありました
there might be a frame
with a painted door on the stage,
ご丁寧に呼び鈴まで
付けられることもありました
and maybe even a doorbell
for the publisher to ring.
Now, if the householder
was supposed to be interested,
家の人が関心を示すだろうということは
すぐに分かりました
you knew it
because the house number was 777.
家の番号が777だったからです
And if the householder
was going to be opposed,
家の人が敵対的な場合も分かりました
you knew that as well
because the house number would be 666.
家の番号が666だったからです
Now, on one program that I remember,
ある実演を思い出します
伝道者がドアをノックすると
司祭の格好をした兄弟が出てきます
the publisher knocks on the door
and a brother dressed as a priest answers.
三位一体について議論を吹っ掛けます
He puts up a real argument about the Trinity.
Talk about visual aids
大胆な演出ですね
—but you never forgot what you saw and heard!
でも1度見たら忘れられない
視覚教材です
これは覚えていますか 昔は会衆に
会衆の僕と ほかに7人の僕がいました
And do you remember when
each congregation had a congregation servant
and up to seven other servants:
the assistant congregation servant,
the Bible study servant,
会衆の僕の補佐 聖書研究の僕
the accounts servant,
the Watchtower{
会計の僕 「ものみの塔」研究の僕
the magazine-territory servant,
the literature servant,
雑誌と区域の僕 文書の僕
神権宣教学校の僕です
and the Theocratic Ministry School servant?
Now, at that time,
apart from book study conductors,
それで 書籍研究の司会者を除くと
you couldn’t have more than
eight servants in the congregation.
会衆で奉仕する僕は最高8人でした
誰かが引っ越して空きができない限り
So unless someone moved,
a young man had no chance
of becoming a servant.
若い兄弟は僕になれませんでした
So how could a young man
reach out for more responsibility?
では 若い兄弟には責任を
担う道がないのでしょうか
And how would the prophecy recorded
それに ミカ 5:5に
記されている預言は
at Micah 5:5 ever be fulfilled?
どのように実現するのでしょうか
There Jehovah promised:
エホバはこう約束していました
“We will raise up against him
seven shepherds,
「私たちはアッシリア人に対して
7人の牧者 いや
8人の高官を立てる」
yes, eight princes of mankind.”
7は完全にそろっているという意味です
Well, seven represents completeness.
So eight princes—that would indicate
ですから8人の高官とは
会衆を教え導く兄弟たちが
that there would be
more than enough men in the congregations
十分過ぎるほどいるということです
to provide theocratic direction.
But how could that be
when there was basically
でも 会衆で8人の僕しか
奉仕できないのであれば
a limit of eight servants per congregation?
どうしたらいいのでしょう
答えは1971年に与えられました
The answer came in 1971.
We were thrilled when we understood
会衆で長老団が奉仕するようになること
that each congregation has a body of elders,
また長老や奉仕の僕の数に
上限がないことを知って
and there is no set number
of elders or ministerial servants.
うれしく思いました 資格があれば
誰でも任命されるのです
As many as are qualified can be appointed.
私が66年前にバプテスマを受けた時
Now, when I was baptized 66 years ago,
you didn’t have to be approved
for baptism by the congregation.
会衆の僕たちの承認を得る
必要はありませんでした
The only questions asked
of baptism candidates
バプテスマ希望者が答えるのは
バプテスマの話の最後に
行われる2つの質問だけでした
were the two they answered
at the conclusion of the baptism talk.
それで 時には兄弟たちが
びっくりするようなことも起きました
That led to a few strange situations.
On a few occasions
バプテスマの話が終わる頃
—much to the surprise of the servants—
someone would rush up
誰かが会場の前の方に急いでやって来て
to the front of the hall at the end
of the baptism talk,
2つの質問に答え
answer the two questions,
バプテスマを受けたのです
and get baptized.
Something more was needed
しかしバプテスマを受けるには
—assurance that the individual
really knew what he was doing
バプテスマの意味をよく理解し
聖書の原則に沿って
生活していることが求められます
and especially that he was living
in harmony with Scriptural principles.
それで 1967年に
バプテスマ希望者が
So in 1967,
questions were provided
so that the responsible brothers
本当にバプテスマを受ける資格が
あるかどうかを確認するための質問が
could be assured that each candidate
was truly qualified for baptism.
準備されました
その後 それらの質問は何度か調整され
Those questions have been refined
over the years.
And today, we go over some 60 questions
今はバプテスマ希望者と60ほどの
質問を討議することになっています
with baptism candidates.
The copper has turned to gold.
銅が金に替わったのです
出版物にあまり挿絵が
なかったことを覚えていますか
Do you remember when there were
very few pictures in our publications?
挿絵があっても たいていは
白黒か 2色の絵でした
And the few that we had
were usually in black and white
or only two colors.
今ではフルカラーの魅力的な
出版物が作られています
Today, our spiritual food
is served in attractive publications
in full color.
Now, those of us who’ve served
外国語会衆で奉仕してきた兄弟姉妹は
in foreign-language congregations
will also remember
新しい出版物が英語で出ても
when a new publication in English
自分が学んでいる言語のものは
might not be available
in another language for several years.
何年も待つ必要があったことを
覚えているでしょう
Study articles trailed by several months.
研究記事も何カ月か待ちました
Now, that’s before it became possible
for the branches
各地の支部では 同時出版が
まだ行われていませんでした
to do simultaneous printing.
So here’s how it worked.
当時はこんな感じでした
Material in English
would be mailed to the branches
英語の原稿が翻訳のために
各地の支部に郵送されます
by regular mail for translation.
If the translators had a question
about the meaning of a sentence in English,
翻訳者たちが英語の文章の
意味について尋ねたい場合
they would use regular mail
to send their question to headquarters.
質問の手紙を本部に郵送します
その後本部は回答を支部に送ります
In time, headquarters would answer back
by regular mail.
This back and forth
—it could take quite a while.
こういうやり取りには
かなりの時間がかかりました
And in some countries, mail service was poor.
郵便事情が悪い国もありました
今では 兄弟姉妹が開発した
特別なプログラムのおかげで
Now, today,
thanks to special computer programs
that our brothers have developed
電子的にやり取りが
できるようになりました
and the ability to communicate electronically
ほかにもさまざまな点が改善され
and some other factors, we’re able to release
most language editions simultaneously
with the English.
ほとんどの言語が英語と同時出版
できるようになりました
What an improvement!
何という進歩でしょう
次のことはご存じでしたか
Now, speaking of our literature,
do you realize that it’s been some 31 years
会衆内外を問わず
出版物のための寄付を
求めないという決定が
since the decision was made
that in the United States
米国で下されてから
かれこれ31年ほどになります
we’d no longer ask
for a contribution for our literature?
Later, the arrangement
was extended worldwide.
やがて全世界でそのように
することになりました
That’s been a real blessing for our brothers!
兄弟姉妹はこのことを本当に喜びました
For example,
例えば 出版物のための
寄付が求められていた頃
when we were asking
for contributions for literature,
some brothers in Africa and other places
アフリカなどの兄弟たちの中には
家族全員分の「ものみの塔」を
入手できない人たちがいました
couldn’t afford to have a Watchtower
f{
They were just too poor.
とても貧しかったからです
And what about bound books?
製本など手に入りません
こんなことがありました
I’ll tell you an experience.
アフリカのある宣教者は
1人の若い兄弟が
In one African country, a missionary noticed
that a young brother quoted
a wide variety of scriptures
コメントでいろいろな聖句を
使っていることに気付きました
in his comments, and he got curious.
感心した宣教者はこう尋ねました
One day, he asked the young brother,
「どうしてそんなにたくさんの
聖句を知っているの？」
“How did you come to know
so many scriptures?”
The brother replied:
“It’s the Reasoning boo{
若い兄弟は 「『論じる』の本があるときに
いつも読んでいるんです」と答えました
I read it every chance I get.”
The missionary asked him, “What do you mean
宣教者は 「本があるときに読むって
どういう意味？」と尋ねました
you read it every chance you get?”
若い兄弟は言いました
Well, he replied:
“I don’t have a Reasoning bo{
「僕は『論じる』の本を持ってないんです
お金がないので
“I could never afford one.
でも 『論じる』の本を持っている
姉妹がいるので 時々借りています
“But I know a sister who has one,
“and she lets me borrow it from time to time.
I read it every chance I get.”
借りている間はいつも
読むようにしているんです」
宣教者はどうしたでしょうか
Well, you can imagine,
すぐに「論じる」の本と
the missionary went out
and bought him a Reasoning {
「新世界訳聖書」を
若い兄弟にプレゼントしました
and a New World Translation {
It was a great investment.
そうするだけの価値がありました
その後 若い兄弟は
どうなったでしょうか
The young brother
was later called into Bethel,
and where do you think he was assigned?
ベテルに招待され
文書部門に割り当てられました
To the literature department.
The brothers knew
that he appreciated the literature so much
兄弟は文書の大切さが
よく分かっていたので
会衆に必要な文書が届くように
一生懸命に奉仕しました
that he’d make sure the congregations
had the literature they needed.
Well, looking back,
振り返ってみると どの取り決めも
we can see that the arrangements
back then served a purpose.
その時のニーズにかなったものでした
They were like fine copper.
良質の銅のようなものです
We do not look down on them.
私たちは劣ったものとは見ていません
むしろ ゼカリヤ 4:10に
あるような見方をしています
Rather, we take the view expressed
at Zechariah 4:10:
“Who has despised the day
「小さな始まりの日を
軽く見たのは誰か」
of small beginnings?”
Now, as those taking the lead
saw a better way of doing things,
でも 責任を持つ兄弟たちは
より良い方法を見つけると
ためらわずに調整しました
they didn’t hesitate to make adjustments.
That’s very faith-strengthening.
本当に信仰が強まります
これからも より良いものに
なっていくことでしょう
And the best is yet to come!
最初に述べた通り 皆さんにとって
初めて聞く話もあったかもしれません
As I mentioned in the beginning,
this may be the first time that some of you
have heard about these things.
長年奉仕している人に
Why not ask someone
who has been in the truth for many years
真理を学んだ頃のことを
尋ねてみるのはどうですか
what it was like
when he was new in the truth?
That could lead
to a very stimulating discussion!
きっと 楽しくて励みになる
エピソードをたくさん聞けるでしょう
Thank you
興味深い歴史を話してくださり
ありがとうございました
for those historical insights, David.
When you think about
これまで 本当に大きな
変化がありました
how much has changed just in our lifetimes,
ここ数十年の間にです
エホバは確かに ご自分の組織を
you really see how Jehovah
keeps improving his organization.
絶えずより良いものにしています
Next, we have a great example
では ある兄弟の手本に注目しましょう
ジョン･ミルズ兄弟です
of someone who has seen all of the changes
兄弟は これまで取り上げた
さまざまな変化を見てきました
we’ve talked about and more: John Mills.
個人的にも大きな変化がありました
Let’s see how he
has faithfully served Jehovah
兄弟は長年 さまざまな割り当てを
忠実に果たしてきました
through multiple assignments and challenges.
でも 難しい問題もありました
私には3人の姉がいます
I was raised with three sisters,
and my mom was in the truth.
母が真理を教えてくれました
I remember sitting on the sofa
よくソファーに座って
and just talking about spiritual things
with my mom.
母と聖書のことを話したのを
思い出します
母は「どんな割り当ても 感謝して
大切にするんだよ」と教えてくれました
And she taught us to appreciate
any assignment that we had
—to see it as something very special.
Pioneering was my life.
開拓奉仕は私の生きがいでした
ギレアデに行けば他の人にもっと
与えることができると思いました
Gilead to me was a way to give to others
—to be very busy in service.
奉仕に打ち込めます
エホバにこう祈りました
I prayed to Jehovah.
I said, “I really want to go to Gilead
「ギレアデに行きたいです
but, if it’s possible, to have a wife too.”
そして もしできれば
妻も与えてください」
And I just thought, ‘Boy, are you pushy!’
でもそうお願いしてから ちょっと
厚かましいかなと思いました
You know, and so—
でも エホバは願いを
かなえてくれました
But Jehovah gave me that.
I went to Gilead.
そしてギレアデに行きました
And to my amazement,
驚いたことに
すごくきれいで信仰の強い姉妹が
there was the most lovely, spiritual sister,
同じクラスにいたんです
a student in the same class, Lois.
ロイスです
I met her and was able to marry her
私たちは ギレアデを卒業して
1週間後に結婚しました
one week after Gilead.
Arriving as a newlywed couple
宣教者ホームでほかの7人と一緒に
in a missionary home with seven other people
新婚生活をスタートさせるのはちょっと
と思うかもしれませんが
was quite daunting.
But we didn’t let that faze us;
we were on our honeymoon.
私たちは平気でした
ハネムーン気分でした
コロンビアでの伝道は最高です
Colombia was a paradise spiritually.
満喫しました
We loved it so much!
This was the kind of life we wanted.
願っていた生き方です
Lois was a great teacher in the ministry.
ロイスは人々を教えるのが
とても上手でした
私をよく支えてくれて
I always enjoyed working with her;
she was actually a great support for me.
一緒に奉仕をするのが楽しかったです
コロンビアは治安がとても悪いです
Obviously, Colombia had its risks.
時には 状況が非常に悪化しました
I remember in the mornings,
sometimes it got to the point when
I would look at Lois and she would look
at me and we’d just say,
朝 出掛ける時にお互いの顔を見て
「もし何かあったら楽園で会おうね」
と言うこともありました
“If I don’t see you, see you
in the Paradise,” you know?
Colombia became our home.
コロンビアは第二の
ふるさとになりました
We traveled the length and breadth
いろいろな割り当てで
国中を旅行しました
of the country
in our different assignments.
コロンビアでの奉仕を始めて
20年余りたった頃
We had been over 20 years in Colombia
when it became very evident
ロイスの母親を世話する
必要が生じました
that Lois’s mom would need our care.
そのためにはコロンビアを
離れなければなりません
This, of course,
would mean leaving our assignment.
コロンビアを去るのは胸が
張り裂けるような思いでした
It almost tore my heart apart
to leave Colombia.
I felt I was abandoning so many privileges
たくさんの奉仕の割り当てを
手放すのは寂しいことでした
and my treasured assignment.
どれも愛着のある奉仕だったので
In the U.S.A.,
米国に行ってからも
we were working as a team,
2人で協力しました
and I could see Lois really organized,
ロイスは置かれた状況でベストを尽くし
何でも計画的に行いました
making the best of the situation.
Helping her mom
母親を本当によく世話していました
was really the source,
そうすることに深い喜びを
感じていました
in a way, of her deep joy.
Helping others was just a way of life
他の人を助けるのが
ロイスの生き方でした
to Lois.
It doesn’t matter what privilege you have
どんな立場や責任を与えられているかは
and what responsibility;
重要ではありません
true happiness
本当の幸せというものは
is always found in giving.
与えることから得られます
Really, Lois got very ill.
その後 ロイスは重い病気になりました
Lois never cried about her illness
でも 病気のことで泣いたり
自分を哀れんだりしませんでした
or felt sorry for herself.
She always was focused on others
いつもほかの人のことを考え
and would give of herself, even
助けになろうとしていました
痛みを感じる時も そうしていたんです
within the pain of illness.
Now that Lois has passed,
ロイスは亡くなりました
今でも ロイスの立派な
生き方のことをよく考えます
many times I think of her example,
そうすると 自分も
頑張ろうという気持ちになります
and it just motivates me to carry on.
この中央アメリカ支部では
Here at the Central America branch
素晴らしい兄弟姉妹と
一緒に奉仕しています
I am surrounded by such a loving family.
私の家族です
I resolved when
妻を亡くすという経験をした時
I went through this situation
心に決めたことがあります
つらい経験をしている
兄弟姉妹に気付いたなら
with losing my wife to find others
一緒に時間を過ごすことです
that were in similar situations
and maybe sit down for a coffee.
座ってコーヒーでも
飲みながら話をします
Just that fellow feeling
仲間の兄弟姉妹を気遣い
of just being able
思いやり 励ますことは
to show interest and to encourage
another person is a great joy
私にとって大きな喜びです
そして 私自身が難しい状況を
耐え忍ぶ上で
that I personally find one
of the most helpful things
to endure trials.
とても助けになっています
長年エホバに忠実に仕えてきた
ミルズ兄弟の姿を見て
John’s life of faithful service reminds me
コリント第二 1:3, 4の言葉の
通りだと思いました こうあります
of the truth found at 2 Corinthians 1:3, 4:
“[Jehovah] comforts us in all our trials
「［エホバは］私たちがどんな試練に
遭うとしても慰めてくださいます
“so that we may be able to comfort others
それで私たちは 神からの慰めにより
“in any sort of trial with the comfort
どんな試練に遭う人をも
慰めることができます」
that we receive from God.”
Have you ever wondered
さて こう思ったことはありますか
why we sing at our meetings?
「集会で歌を歌うのはなぜだろう
地区大会はどうしていつも
夏に開かれるのだろう」
or why we attend conventions,
usually in the summer?
若い皆さんやバプテスマを
受けて間もない方は
Many who are young in years
or new in the truth
エホバの証人の歴史について
詳しく知らないかもしれません
may not be familiar
with certain aspects of our history.
Yet, this rich spiritual history
エホバの証人の歴史は貴重な財産です
皆さんの相続財産です
is your heritage,
ぜひ受け取ってほしいと思います
and we want you to become acquainted with it.
So the Governing Body
それで 統治体の承認の下
has approved the development of a new series:
新しいシリーズが
始まることになりました
Our History in Motion.
「JWヒストリー」です
Each segment will look at an aspect
毎回 私たちの崇拝の
1つの面が取り上げられます
of our worship through time,
スプレーン兄弟の話も
興味深かったですね
similar to what David shared with us earlier.
The series will help us see
このシリーズを通して
私たちの崇拝の基盤が
that our worship is rooted,
伝統や習慣ではなく
not in tradition or custom,
but in the truth found in God’s Word.
神の言葉の真理であることが
分かるでしょう
Now, for our first episode,
これから見る第1回では
it looks at the history
of singing praises to Jehovah.
エホバを賛美する歌の歴史を
取り上げたいと思います
それは極秘に作られ
It was made in secret,
ジャケットの裏地に隠され
hidden in the lining of a jacket,
ひそかに国外に運ばれました
and then smuggled out of the country.
What was it?
何がですか
A recording
of brothers and sisters in Siberia
シベリアの兄弟姉妹が歌った
王国の歌の録音テープです
singing Kingdom songs.
They sent it from one side
of the earth to the other
このテープは地球の反対側に運ばれ
to be played at the 1958
international convention in New York
1958年にニューヨークで開かれた
国際大会で流されました
for an audience of more than 250,000 people.
25万人以上の聴衆が
それを聞いたのです
歌うことがエホバの証人にとって
それほど大切なのはなぜですか
Why is singing so important
to Jehovah’s Witnesses?
Let’s find out in this episode
of Our History in Motion.
「JWヒストリー」の第1回を
ご覧ください
エホバを崇拝する人たちは何千年もの間
Jehovah’s worshippers
have long praised him with song.
歌でエホバを賛美してきました
But how did singing become
では現代 どんないきさつで
a part of our modern-day worship?
崇拝のために歌うように
なったのでしょうか
The story begins more than 150 years ago.
話は150年以上前にさかのぼります
The year is about 1869
1869年
in Allegheny, Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
米国ペンシルバニア州アレゲーニーで
Charles Taze Russell
若いチャールズ･テイズ･ラッセルは
is a young man
searching for Scriptural truth.
聖書の真理を探し求めていました
One evening he’s walking along
and hears something
ある晩 道を歩いていると
地下の部屋から賛美歌が
聞こえてきました
—singing coming from a religious meeting
being held in a basement.
中に入って話を聞くと
He goes in, and what he hears sparks a fire
それまでにないほど聖書を学びたい
という気持ちが強まりました
for Bible study like never before.
その後 ラッセルと仲間たちは
Later, Russell and his associates
聖書の真理をいっそう理解し
make music’s role in pure worship clear
清い崇拝で音楽を使うようになりました
as they rediscover Bible truth.
Charles Taze Russell
ラッセルの父親は一時期
音楽に関係した仕事をしていました
may have come to appreciate
how the power of music can stir emotions
そういうこともあってラッセルは
音楽には感情を動かす
大きな力があることを
from a music business
that his father owned for a period of time.
よく知っていたのかもしれません
He believed that “the singing of the truth
「真理を述べた歌を歌うのは
神の民にとって真理を心と頭の中に
収める良い方法」だと思っていました
“is a good way to get it into the heads
and hearts of God’s people.”
The first issue of Zion’s Watch Tower,
1879年7月に出版された
published in July of 1879,
「シオンのものみの塔」の創刊号で
announced a songbook
最初の歌の本が発表されました
—the first of many to come.
「花嫁の歌」という本です
It was called Songs of the Bride.
It contained 144 hymns,
144曲の賛美歌が収められていました
or religious songs of praise.
聖書研究者たちはその本を使って
The Bible Students sang
at their meetings and assemblies.
集会や大会で歌いました
1900年代初め
What was it like to sing
these songs back in the early 1900’s?
そうした歌はどんな感じで
歌われていたのでしょうか
Imagine that you’re
at one of Charles Taze Russell’s lectures.
チャールズ･テイズ･ラッセルの講演会に
来たところを想像してみてください
As you walk in,
you’re handed a small sheet of paper.
中に入ると 小さな紙を渡されます
You look for a seat, but it’s packed.
席を探しますが 満席です
As the crowd quiets down,
聴衆が静かになると
講演会は歌と祈りで
始まることが知らされます
they announce that the meeting
will start with a song and prayer.
In a church,
you expect to find a hymn book in your pew,
一般の教会の座席には
賛美歌の本がありますが
but this is a rented hall.
ここは借りた会場です
Then you realize
that the paper you were handed
先ほど受け取った紙を見ると
歌の歌詞が書かれています
has the song lyrics,
聖書を学びたい人が自分の名前と
住所を書く欄もあります
and it also has a place
to leave your name and address
if you’d like a Bible study.
聴衆が歌い始めると
あなたもそれに加わります
So when the audience
starts to sing, you join in.
当時の歌はどんな
感じだったのでしょうか
What did songs sound like back then?
80年以上歌われた
ある歌を聞いてみましょう
Let’s listen to a song
we sang for over eight decades.
1916年に録音された
「たたえよ」という歌です
Here’s a recording from 1916.
That’s a little different than how
今の歌とはちょっと雰囲気が違いますね
our songs sound today.
Compare different versions of this song,
この歌は 長年の間に
歌詞やタイトルが何度か変わりました
and you’ll notice that the lyrics
and theme changed over the years.
これは1935年のものです
Here’s a version of “All Hail”
by the Watch Tower Male Quartet in 1935.
ものみの塔男性四重唱団が歌っています
最初の歌の本では この歌は
In our first songbook this song was called
「イエスの御名の力をたたえよ」
という題でした
“All Hail the Power of Jesus’ Name,”
which was about, well,
イエスの名の力について歌ったもので
the power of Jesus’ name
エホバは全く出てきません
with zero mention of Jehovah.
You see, many songs prior to this
当時の歌の多くは 一般の教会の
賛美歌がベースになっていました
were adapted from existing church hymns.
Now here’s the same song in 1950.
同じ歌の1950年版です
Instead of the lyrics
イエスの名を過度に強調するのではなく
overemphasizing Jesus’ name,
神の望むことを知らせるよう
勧める歌詞になっていて
the lyrics refer to “making known God’s will”
エホバの名が出てきます
and mention Jehovah by name.
なぜ変わったのでしょうか
Why all the changes?
Because our songs reflect
聖書の真理の最新の理解に
合わせるためです
our current understanding
of Scriptural truth.
光が明るさを増すにつれ
As the light gets brighter,
真理をいっそう理解できるようになり
歌も変わりました
we understand the truth more clearly,
so the songs change.
最初の歌の本には
Our first songbook explained
「間違った教えの影響を受けていない歌」
を出版することを
explained the goal to publish
“songs free from objectionable theology,”
目指している と述べられています
and it’s been the case ever since.
今も同じことを目指しています
We don’t hold on to songs
私たちは 伝統や愛着に
縛られることはありません
for tradition or nostalgia.
We sing them because it’s the truth!
私たちが歌うのは真理の歌です
1928年の歌の本は
From the 1928 songbook onward,
大きな転換点になりました
there was a big shift.
Many songs were written
by our brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹の作った歌がたくさん
使われるようになったのです
They put more emphasis on Jehovah’s name,
エホバの名 性質 王国にいっそう
注意が向けられるようになりました
his attributes, and his Kingdom.
You can even tell by the title
本のタイトルも
「エホバに奉る讃歌」となっています
Songs of Praise to Jehovah.
Some of the songs might even sound familiar,
この歌のように 皆さんもご存じの
歌も含まれていました
like this one.
ご両親はエホバの証人ですか
おじいさん おばあさん
Are your parents in the truth?
your grandparents?
even your great-grandparents?
ひいおじいさん ひいおばあさん
の代からですか
If so, they sang the same song as you
もしそうなら 集会や大会で
代々同じ歌を歌ってきたことになります
at their meetings and assemblies.
That’s a real legacy!
まさに相続財産です
では 1940年代の
状況を見てみましょう
Let’s fast-forward to the 1940’s.
信仰ゆえに投獄されていた
兄弟たちもいます
Some of our brothers
were imprisoned for their faith.
The world was at war and needed good news.
世界大戦が行われており
良い知らせが必要でした
So we intensified
宣教活動が強化され
our preaching and teaching work.
This is when
the Watchtower Bible School of Gilead
ものみの塔ギレアデ聖書学校と
神権宣教学校が始まりました
and the Theocratic Ministry School started,
and it’s also when
singing was reintroduced at our meetings.
そして 集会で再び歌が
歌われるようになりました
Wait a minute!
えっ？歌が再び歌われるようになった？
Reintroduced?
That means we stopped singing at meetings.
実は 集会で歌が歌われていない
時期があったのです
When?
いつのことですか
Find out in the next episode
次回の「JWヒストリー」をお楽しみに
of Our History in Motion.
うーん 続きが楽しみです
Well, that’s a cliff-hanger!
Would you like to know
歌が歌われていなかった
時期があるなんて
why we stopped singing for a time?
ちょっと意外ですね
You’ll want to watch
the second part of this video.
続きはパート2をご覧ください
近いうちにjw.orgに
アップされます
It will be posted soon on jw.org.
今後「JWヒストリー」では
And look for future episodes
さまざまな内容が取り上げられます
of Our History in Motion.
楽しみですね
Many years ago,
40年ほど前の「目ざめよ！」に
Awake!{
エリザベス･バルネーブ姉妹の
ライフ･ストーリーが載せられています
published the story of Elizabeth Balnave.
Elizabeth explains
バルネーブ姉妹は 自分の生き方を
大きく変えた理由を述べています
why she made a major career decision.
How did that decision affect her life?
その後 姉妹は
どうしているのでしょうか
Let’s find out in this episode
今回の「あの人は今」をご覧ください
of Where Are They Now?
姉妹のその後が分かります
As a child, I dreamed
子供の頃から
バレリーナになるのが夢でした
of becoming a ballerina.
I trained as a ballet dancer from childhood.
それで 幼いうちから
レッスンを始めました
I was taught to give complete obedience
to the artistic director,
ディレクターへの絶対的な服従と
absolute loyalty to the dance company,
バレエ団への忠誠をたたき込まれました
and to put ballet before everything else
in my life.
バレエを何よりも優先することもです
I finally realized there’s no way
to get ahead in this world
この世界で成功するには 全てのものを
犠牲にしなければなりません
without compromise.
It just can’t be done.
でもそんなの無理ですし
Such a life is empty and unsatisfying.
そのような生き方はむなしいだけです
でも そういう世界に足を踏み入れると
The problem is, once you get into that,
きらびやかな生き方に
魅了されてしまいます
you get lulled in by that glamour and glitz.
そのまま進んでいって
Now, down the road
when you finally see the trap
自分がコントロールされている
だけだと気付いても
and what you got into,
it’s very hard to get out.
そこから抜け出すのは大変です
私は若い人たちに
よく言っているんですが
And I always tell young people, you know,
この世界での成功がどんなに
素晴らしいものに見えても
that it doesn’t matter how good everything
seems; it doesn’t matter how great.
There’s always a string attached—always.
その釣り糸の先には
鋭い釣り針が付いています
And then one day,
you’re going to wake up and it’s a rope.
ある時 がんじがらめになっている
自分に気付きます
And you can’t cut a rope that easily
そこから抜け出すのは大変です
—meaning you can’t get out of the situation
サタンのわなは強力なので
そう簡単には出られません
once Satan has you trapped in it.
And it happens without you even realizing it.
気付かないうちにそうなってしまいます
バレエには厳しい練習が必要です
Ballet is discipline,
and I had to figure out a way
でも何とかしてスキルを身に付け
それを実践できるように
なる必要があります
to take that skill
and transfer it into my everyday life.
時間はかかりましたが
できるようになりました
It took some time,
but I finally figured it out,
練習すれば結果は付いてきます
because it’s not a waste.
It’s good.
But what I had to learn
was to get out of my comfort zone.
でも並大抵の努力では
スキルは身に付きません
1987年までベテルで奉仕しました
We were in Bethel until 1987.
Jack had a job lined up when we left Bethel,
and that was good.
ベテルを出た後 夫はすぐに
仕事を始めることができました
I couldn’t get a job
because of my physical health issues.
でも私は健康上の問題があって
働けませんでした
I probably was in bed for about five months.
5カ月ぐらいずっと寝込んでいました
その後 体調はだんだん良くなりました
Eventually, I started feeling better,
and that’s when I realized
how bad the medical bills were getting.
でも治療費が大変なことに
なっていました
とても寝てはいられないと思い
パートタイムの仕事を探しました
I just dragged myself out of bed
and went and looked for a part-time job.
Obviously, through all of this,
Jack and I just kept praying.
夫と私はエホバにずっと祈っていました
エホバが必ず助けてくれる
と信じていました
We knew Jehovah would take care of us.
No question about that.
何とか 法律事務所で
働けることになりました
Eventually, I did get a job at a law firm.
とてもいい仕事でした
30年働きました
It was a good job.
I actually lasted there 30 years.
エホバは私の努力を
本当に祝福してくれました
Absolutely Jehovah blessed me,
and I believe what he was blessing
were my efforts.
仕事を頑張って続けました
I didn’t quit, and I refused to compromise.
でもいつもエホバを第一にしました
新しい仕事にもだんだん慣れて
When I started seeing
that I was really learning this new skill
やり方も分かってきたので
こう祈りました
and I was getting good at it,
「エホバ 私はこの新しい
仕事を覚えました
that’s when I sat down and I said:
“Well, Jehovah, I have this new skill.
あなたのために活用したいです」
I want to be able to use it for you.”
One thing led to another, and I became
やがて ベテルの法律部門で
a commuter Bethelite
for the Legal Department.
コミューターとして
働くようになりました
I’d say that about 11 years
after I had left Bethel,
ベテルを出て 11年後だと思いますが
仕事中に突然具合が悪くなりました
I was working and all of a sudden,
I got sick again with the same thing
以前と同じように体重が減って
体力がなくなってしまいました
—complete rapid loss of weight
and all the weakness came back.
I was eventually diagnosed
as having celiac disease.
医師によると
セリアック病ということでした
So once I changed my diet,
I just started getting better and better.
食事療法によって
徐々に良くなっていきました
2014年まで法律事務所で働きました
I stayed with the law firm until 2014,
and then my husband and I retired
and moved to another part of the country.
夫も退職したので
別の場所に引っ越しました
And now, currently,
I’m a remote Bethel consultant.
今はベテル･コンサルタント
として奉仕しています
If you slave for the world,
you really are a slave.
世に仕える人は文字通り奴隷です
If you slave for Jehovah,
でも エホバに奴隷として仕える人は
実際には自由です
in my opinion, you’re not slaving at all.
エホバに仕えるなら幸せになれます
You couldn’t have a better partnership
than you and Jehovah,
and that’s how I view it.
エホバと共に働けるなんて最高です
And you’re never going to experience
Jehovah to the full
エホバを本当に身近に感じるためには
エホバのために一歩
踏み出す必要があります
unless you put yourself out there
for him to use.
I’ve had a wonderful life
エホバに一生懸命仕えることで
of extraordinary spiritual privileges.
素晴らしい人生を送ってきました
ほかのどんな生き方とも
比べものになりません
There’s no career in the world
that is ever going to come close to that.
姉妹が頑張ってこれたのはなぜですか
Wouldn’t you say that resilience
is one of the qualities
that has helped Elizabeth?
1つには めげない心を
持っていたからです
What can each of us do
どうすれば私たちも
めげない心を持てますか
to be more resilient?
Notice three practical suggestions
3つの役立つ点を
ガイユス･グロッケンティン兄弟が
朝の崇拝で話してくださいました
in this morning worship presented
by Brother Gajus Glockentin.
Mary kept listening to what Jesus was saying.
マリアはイエスが話すのを
ずっと聞いていました
How commendable!
立派です
She set the right priorities
正しい優先順位を持っていました
and is a good example for us.
良い手本です
Martha, her sister, however,
でも姉妹のマルタは
received loving correction from Jesus,
コメント文にある通り
イエスから愛ある助言を受けました
as our printed comment puts it.
Now let us, today, put ourselves
in the shoes of Martha for a moment.
今日は少し マルタの身になって
考えてみましょう
She showed great interest in supporting Jesus
イエスがユダヤの大変な地域で
宣教を行っていた間
by providing him a base during his ministry
マルタはイエスを家に泊めて
一生懸命にサポートしました
in the difficult area of Judea.
Now this time,
今回イエスが家に来る前
Mary and Martha
were probably working together
マリアとマルタは恐らく一緒に
準備をしていたことでしょう
to prepare things for Jesus.
But after Jesus arrived,
Mary stopped helping as our text indicates.
でもイエスが来ると マリアは
手伝うのをやめてしまいます
How did Martha feel about it?
マルタはどう感じたでしょうか
Now she had to care for everything herself.
自分一人で準備しなければなりません
Can we imagine the tension rising
恐らくマルタは心穏やかでは
いられなかったことでしょう
within Martha’s heart?
The stress level is increased,
いらいらしてきたに違いありません
and her dear sister
sits and listens to Jesus.
姉妹のマリアはイエスのもとから
離れようとしません
So she asked Jesus to correct Mary,
それでマルタはイエスに
マリアに「手伝うよう
言ってください」と頼みます
to order her back to work.
But to her surprise, she, Martha,
received counsel from Jesus.
でも驚いたことに 自分がイエスから
助言を受けてしまいます
How would we feel in such a situation?
あなただったらどう感じますか
We are doing something well-intentioned
善かれと思ってしているのに
and, yet, instead of commendation,
we receive counsel.
褒め言葉ではなく
助言を受けてしまいます
Maybe our eyes filled with tears.
目には涙があふれるかもしれません
We feel the pain in our chest.
ショックのあまり
We might think we can’t breathe anymore.
胸が苦しくなるかもしれません
Did Martha think for a moment,
replying to Jesus, saying:
マルタはイエスに
こう言いたくなったでしょうか
“This is not fair!
「ひどいです！あなたのために
頑張っているのに 助言ですか
“I am doing everything to support you,
and now this.
“You know, from now on,
I am listening too,
じゃあこれからは私も話を聞きます
and I am curious to find out
who prepares the meals for you.”
でも食事は誰が準備して
くださるんでしょうね」
Of course, we don’t know
what Martha thought and said.
もちろんマルタが何を考え
どう言ったかは分かりません
But what we do know,
as our printed comment puts it,
でも分かっているのは
コメント文にある通り
she took to heart Jesus’ loving correction.
マルタがイエスの愛ある助言を
銘記したということです
What can help us
to overcome such a painful moment
では つらい気持ちを克服し
前に進むために
何が助けになりますか
and to progress?
The term often used in this connection
よく言われるのは
「めげない心」を持つことです
is “resilience.”
People who are resilient
are able to recover easily and quickly
めげない心を持つ人は
うれしくないことや
傷つくようなことがあっても
from unpleasant and damaging events.
すぐに立ち直れます
It is like the ability of this piece of metal
ちょうど このばねのような
力があります
to tolerate pressure
プレッシャーがあってもそれに耐え
and go back to its original form.
元の形に戻ることができます
Let us, therefore,
look at three factors that make us resilient
ではどうすればめげない心を持つ人
すぐに諦めない人になれますか
and different from those
who easily give up and surrender.
3つの点を考えましょう
Now, the first factor is facing reality
まず1つ目は 事実を直視することです
—facing reality.
事実を直視する
Let us, please,
open to Proverbs chapter 28.
格言 28章を開いてみましょう
The question we are asking ourselves
in a difficult moment is this:
難しい状況の時にはこう自問すべきです
‘Do I truly understand and accept
the reality of my situation?’
「自分の状況を本当に理解し
受け入れているだろうか」
格言 28:26にはこうあります
Here, at Proverbs 28:26,
it starts by saying:
前半に注目してください
“Whoever trusts in his own heart
「自分に頼る人は愚かであ［る］」
is stupid.”
We might tend to put on emotional blinders
私たちには 見たくない
ものから目を背け
見たいものだけを見る傾向があります
and see only what we want to see.
Many people slip into denial
as a coping mechanism.
何かがあるとすぐに
自分のせいではない と考えがちです
However, the Proverb continues
in the second part, saying:
でも 先ほどの聖句の
後半にはこうあります
“But the one who walks in wisdom
「知恵によって歩む人は安全である」
will escape.”
This means seeing things the way they are.
ですから 物事をありのままに
見る必要があります
Facing reality
現実を直視します
—really facing reality is grueling work.
現実を直視するのは簡単ではありません
Indeed, it can be unpleasant
時には嫌な気持ちになったり
and often emotionally wrenching.
つらい気持ちになったり
するかもしれません
The apostle Peter had this experience
使徒ペテロはそう感じました
イエスを3度否定し イエスから
見つめられた時のことです
when Jesus looked at him
after Peter had denied him three times.
Peter faced reality, went outside,
でもペテロは事実を直視し
broke down, and wept bitterly.
外に出て泣き崩れました
For sure, he was not looking for any excuses.
言い訳を探そうとしたりは
しませんでした
This experience, as well as other situations
where he received counsel,
この経験によって また他の機会にも
助言を受けたことで
ペテロは進歩し 与えられた仕事を
いっそうよく果たせるようになりました
helped him to make progress
and to fulfill his assignments even better.
Now, what is the second factor?
2つ目は何でしょうか
We call it “meaning-making.”
ポジティブな見方をすることです
We might know people who
under pressure threw up their hands
ある人たちは問題にぶつかると
「どうして自分がこんな目に
遭わなければならないのだろう」と
and cried and said,
“Why is this happening to me?”
思うかもしれません
Such people see themselves as victims,
自分は犠牲者だと思っているので
and living through hardship
does not teach them any lessons.
そうした状況から何も
学ぶことができません
We, however,
based on our Bible knowledge,
でも私たちは聖書を学んでいるので
understand why difficulties
and challenging situations
難しい問題にぶつかることが
あるのはなぜかを知っています
are sometimes unavoidable.
Seeing the bigger picture adds meaning.
物事の全体を見るなら
ポジティブな見方ができます
This helps us, as a resilient person,
めげない心を持ち うれしくない状況や
not only to endure
an unpleasant situation or a new circumstance
新しい状況に置かれても
頑張り続けることができます
but also to look at seeming obstacles
それだけでなく 難しい状況を
and see an opportunity in it.
何かを学ぶチャンスと
見ることができます
We all know that no one is perfect.
誰一人 完全ではありません
Everyone fails at something sometime.
誰もが時折 何かのことで失敗します
So our choice
is the manner in which we respond.
そのような時にどうするかは
私たち次第です
We are actively trying
to make the best out of it,
失敗から学ぶことが大切です
looking ahead rather than behind,
後ろではなく 前に目を向けます
setting goals
—maybe new goals.
目標を持ちます 新しい目標です
We might remember how Brother Harold King
覚えておられると思いますが
ハロルド･キング兄弟は
showed this resilient disposition
独房の中でもめげない態度を示しました
when he was in solitary confinement.
How did he give meaning
to his difficult situation
そうした状況の中で どのように
できることを行ったでしょうか
by making the best out of it?
He said:
こう言っています
“I arranged
for a program of ‘preaching’ activity.
「“伝道”活動の
プログラムを組みました
“But to whom does one preach
when in solitary confinement?
独房の中でだれに
伝道するのかですって？
“I decided that I would build up
some appropriate Bible sermons
私は 記憶していた事柄をもとに
適切な聖書の話を準備し
“from the things I could remember
and then preach to imaginary characters.”
頭の中でいろいろな人に
伝道することにしました」
So in our context, we can say
私たちも ポジティブな
見方を持っていれば
meaning-making is like building a bridge
難しい問題にぶつかっても
トンネルの先の光を見ることができます
from present day hardships
to a better future.
By means of this bridge,
その光が見えていれば
we make a difficult situation manageable.
頑張り続ける力が得られます
We remove the sense
that the present is overwhelming.
もう耐えられない という気持ちに
押しつぶされることはありません
Now let’s look at the third factor:
3つ目は 自分について
a balanced view of ourselves.
バランスの取れた見方を持つことです
Well, we said at the beginning
that we have to face reality
最初に考えた通り 事実を直視すると
つらい気持ちになったり
がっかりしたりすることがあります
which can go along with feelings
of sadness and disappointment.
As resilient people,
でもめげない心を持つ人は
we don’t take a failure
失敗したり間違いを犯したりしても
or a challenging situation personally.
自分に価値がないとは考えません
Let us, please, open to Romans chapter 7,
ローマ 7章を開いてみましょう
because we want to demonstrate this point
使徒パウロの手本から
学ぶことができます
by means of the example of the apostle Paul.
パウロはどんな見方を
していたでしょうか
At times,
he felt discouraged over his weaknesses.
パウロは時折 自分の弱点のために
気落ちしました
Here in chapter 7,
7章を読むと パウロは自分が
罪に束縛されていたために
he describes the pain of conscience
that he suffered
because of feeling captive to sin.
良心の痛みを感じていた
ことが分かります
But then in verse 24,
24節をご覧ください
パウロはこう述べています
he cries out, saying:
“Miserable man that I am!”
「私は実に惨めな人間です！」
Evidently, though, Paul realized
パウロは不完全でした
でもだからといって
that his imperfection did not define him.
自分に価値がないとは考えませんでした
Nine years later,
パウロは9年後 親しい友テモテに
in his second letter to his friend Timothy,
2通目の手紙を書きました
shortly before his death,
死ぬ少し前のことです
he stated
his personal conclusion of the matter
自分の人生を振り返ってこう言いました
here at 2 Timothy 4:7.
テモテ第二 4:7です
こうあります
He said:
“I have fought the fine fight,
「私は立派に戦いました
“I have run the race to the finish,
競走を最後まで走りました
I have observed the faith.”
クリスチャンの信条を守りました」
Paul’s problems and inner struggle
did not miraculously disappear.
パウロの問題や内面の葛藤が
奇跡的になくなることは
ありませんでした
Still, it did not prevent him
でもパウロは諦めることなく
from accomplishing
remarkable things in Jehovah’s service.
エホバへの奉仕を一生懸命に行いました
So, therefore, we do not berate ourselves
ですから 次のようなネガティブな言葉
で自分を責めないようにしましょう
with self-defeating language,
such as “I’m a failure”
「自分は駄目だ」
「自分には価値がない」
or “I’m useless.”
Reflecting on positive aspects of our lives
自分の生活のポジティブな面に目を向け
and reflecting on our strengths
自分の長所について考えるなら
helps us to maintain
a balanced view of ourselves.
自分についてバランスの取れた
見方を保てるでしょう
So in conclusion,
まとめです
マルタの例から めげない心を育て
the experience of Martha reminded us today
保つことの大切さを学びました
of the importance of building
and maintaining resilience
3つの方法があります
by facing reality,
事実を直視すること
ポジティブな見方をすること
meaning-making,
自分についてバランスの取れた
見方を保つことです
and maintaining a balanced view of ourselves.
The Bible contains wonderful descriptions
聖書には パラダイスでの生活が
of how life will be in Paradise.
どれほど素晴らしいかが描かれています
As our new music video shows,
今月のミュージックビデオを
ご覧ください
将来の素晴らしい生活を思い描くと
visualizing these future blessings
brings joy to our heart.
幸せな気持ちになります
I close my eyes, and I can see
A world of peace, love, and harmony.
静かに目を閉じ 心の旅に出よう
一緒に扉 開こう
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
爽やかなそよ風 肩をなでて導く
It’s not a dream, as I’m sure you know.
These things God promised so long ago
少し先へ進もう
Are guaranteed,
Sure to be.
You will see.
さあ ほら 幸せな歌声
Look around—
There’s joy and laughter in ev’ry sound.
Look and see—
This is the way our God meant it to be.
そっと耳すませば 聞こえる
Those who fell asleep along the way,
They live again; we see them ev’ry day.
もういないあの人
会えるんだ また必ず
ずっと一緒にいれる
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
痛みが消えていく 辛い記憶とともに
The pain and crying there used to be
Has gone forever; now it’s history.
みんな 心 躍る
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
さあ ほら 幸せな歌声
Look around—
There’s joy and laughter in ev’ry sound.
そっと耳すませば 聞こえる
Look and see—
This is the way our God meant it to be.
Jehovah’s word is enough for me.
With eyes of faith, it’s reality.
心の目に見える 将来の約束が
道を照らす 優しく
As we see
What’s in store,
You can be sure
Until the moon is no more,
その日まで そう ずっと
When you—
エホバありがとう 今を生きる力
Close your eyes and come with me
To God’s world of peace and harmony.
心晴れる 今日も
Come with me,
And you’ll see.
You will see.
What a beautiful song and video!
なんと美しい歌と映像でしょう
今月のプログラムでは
In our program,
we looked back at theocratic history,
エホバの証人の歴史を振り返りました
not to be nostalgic, but to remind us
思い出に浸るためではなく
エホバが約束通りご自分の組織を
that Jehovah
continually improves his organization,
絶えず良いものにしてきたことを
思い返すためです
just as he promised.
新しいシリーズ
「JWヒストリー」も始まりました
We debuted an exciting new series,
Our History in Motion,
今回は エホバへの崇拝で
and saw the essential role
that singing plays in our worship.
歌うことがどれほど重要かを学びました
We learned
エホバがご自分に仕える人たちを
どのように祝福するかも学びました
how Jehovah blesses those
who serve him.
バルネーブ姉妹はきらびやかな
生活を後にし
Elizabeth gave up
a glamorous career
豊かな祝福を味わってきました
but gained spiritual treasures.
ミルズ兄弟はいろいろな問題を
経験してきましたが
And we saw that although John
has experienced many difficulties,
エホバは兄弟を支えています
Jehovah has helped him
兄弟は他の人を助けることで
喜びを保っています
maintain his joy by helping others.
Before we conclude,
お別れする前に
兄弟姉妹からの
ビデオレターを楽しみましょう
let’s enjoy our video postcard.
This month,
今月はエクアドルの
兄弟姉妹たちを訪ねます
we visit our brothers in Ecuador.
As its name suggests,
エクアドルには赤道という
意味があります
Ecuador is situated on earth’s equator.
文字通り 赤道直下にあります
エクアドルにはガラパゴス諸島や
アンデス山脈があり
It stretches from the Galapagos Islands
to the Andes Mountains
アマゾン川流域も含まれます
and the Amazon River basin.
これはチンボラソ山です
This is Mount Chimborazo.
地球は赤道方向に少し膨らんでいるので
Measured from the center of the earth,
it’s the highest point on our planet
地球の中心からの距離で言えば
世界一高い山です
because of the bulging
of the earth at its equator.
This train line was carved
into the Andes more than a century ago.
これは 100年以上前に造られた
アンデスの山岳鉄道です
1946年に最初に到着した
宣教者たちも
It was used by the first missionaries
who arrived in 1946.
この鉄道を使いました
Today, more than 100,000
現在エクアドルでは
10万人以上のエホバの証人が
of Jehovah’s Witnesses
proclaim the good news in Ecuador.
良い知らせを伝えています
2020年の記念式には
Nearly 300,000 people
attended the Memorial in 2020.
30万人近くの人が出席しました
The Chontapunta Quichua Congregation
チョンタプンタ･キチュア語会衆は
元は孤立したグループでした
began as an isolated group.
兄弟姉妹は生計を立てるため
To support themselves,
our brothers raise flowers
花を育てたり砂金を集めたりしています
and even pan for gold.
でも 一番力を注いでいるのは宣教です
But their zeal is for the ministry.
They go to great lengths
to bear thorough witness in their territory.
徹底的に伝道するためには
努力を惜しみません
橋がなければ別の方法で渡ります
Where bridges aren’t available,
they find a way.
They use two boats, named Enoc
2そうのボート
エノクとエノク2を使って
and Enoc 2, to reach remote
Quichua-speaking communities.
キチュア語を話す人たちが
住む地域に行きます
Remote communities
have poor cellular service.
辺ぴな場所では携帯が
つながりにくいですが
この子はそれにめげずに
電波がよく届く所に行って
That doesn’t stop this Bible student.
Look what he does to get a good signal
集会に出席したり
聖書レッスンを受けたりしています
so he can join meetings and have his study.
To reach those without cellular service,
携帯が使えない所では
the brothers use a high-frequency radio
無線機を使って再訪問や
聖書レッスンをしています
to conduct return visits and Bible studies.
現地語の1つであるワオラニ語でも
講演や記念式の話が行われています
Our brothers have arranged for talks
and the Memorial to be given in Waorani,
an indigenous language
that’s not yet translated.
この言語の文書はまだありません
This little girl, whose family
is part of the congregation,
家族と一緒に会衆で
奉仕しているこの女の子は
shares videos with Waorani-speaking children.
ワオラニ語を話す子供たちに
ビデオを見せています
She is four years old!
まだ4歳です
Our dear brothers and sisters
エクアドルの
チョンタプンタ･キチュア語会衆の
from the Chontapunta Quichua Congregation
in Ecuador
愛する兄弟姉妹が
send their love and greetings
世界中の仲間に
愛とあいさつを送っています
to the worldwide brotherhood.
Leon, my friend,
ウィーバー兄弟 本当に
ありがとうございました
I want to thank you so very much
for helping out with this program.
一緒にプログラムを扱ってくださって
とても助かりました
I really appreciated the help.
私たち2人から 皆さんに温かい
クリスチャン愛を送ります
And together, we send all of you
our warm Christian love.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
this is JW Broadcasting!
JW Broadcastingでした